Guide to the University of Chicago Settlement Records 1897-1977
University of Chicago Library
University of Chicago Settlement. Records
1897-1977
5 linear feet (4 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
The University of Chicago Settlement House was established in 1894 in the packing-house district of Chicago to provide English instruction, citizenship and legal assistance, medical care, and other services, to the largely European immigrant population of the Back of the Yards community. Materials in this collection primarily document the settlement’s programs and activities from the 1930s to the early 1950s.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research.
Historical Note
The University of Chicago Settlement House was established in 1894 by the Philanthropic Committee of the University of Chicago Christian Union in the Back of the Yards neighborhood of Chicago. With previous experience at Hull House, Mary McDowell led the organization as Head Resident and played an integral role in Settlement activities until her death in 1936. The Settlement House provided English instruction, citizenship and legal assistance, and medical care, among many other services, to the largely European immigrant population of the Back of the Yards community. In 1966, the Settlement was merged with the Chicago Commons.
Scope Note
The University of Chicago Settlement collection contains informational literature on the Settlement House and its history, annual and monthly reports, the Settlement League Yearbook, program schedules and brochures, press clippings, article drafts, correspondence, statements and miscellaneous literature.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
Browse finding aids by topic.
Camp Farr. Collection
Chicago Commons. Collection
Hyde Park Historical Society. Collection
Madeline Wallin. Papers
University of Chicago Service League. Records
University of Chicago. Office of the President. Hutchins Administration. Records
Subject Headings
McDowell, Mary E. (Mary Eliza); University of Chicago. Settlement; Social settlements -- Illinois -- Chicago
INVENTORY
- Histories and publications of the Settlement, 1901-1954, Report of the Head Resident, 1901 The University of Chicago Settlement. What is it Actually Doing? What Does It Aim To Do More?, circa 1912 The University of Chicago Settlement, brochure, 1919 Fifty Years at the University of Chicago Settlement, 1944 The University of Chicago Settlement, 1894-1950, typescript, 1950 The University of Chicago Settlement: 60 Years of Service, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Board of Directors, 1945-1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Settlement Reports, 1931-1949 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
- Settlement Program Schedule, 1896-1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Programs and advertisements for events benefitting the Settlement, 1897-1951 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Camp Farr, 1925-1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Press Clippings, 1930-1951 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Public Relations, 1939-1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence and Statements, 1934-1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Miscellaneous, 1927-1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- University of Chicago Settlement League, Year Book, 1912-1944 (Box 2)
- Ledger, 1919-1930 (Box 3)
- Ledger, 1931-1934 (Box 4)
- Calendars of events, October 1940-May 1958 (Box 5)